<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE html [
  <!ENTITY conventions SYSTEM "conventions.xml">
  <!ENTITY syllable SYSTEM "syllable.xml">
  <!ENTITY reflexes SYSTEM "reflexes.xml">
  <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "bibliography.xml">
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#x00a0;"><!-- no-break space -->
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" 
      xmlns:p="http://www.gold-saucer.org/xmlns/chinese-phonology"
      xmlns:s="http://www.gold-saucer.org/xmlns/structured-html"
      lang="en">

<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css">
    <!-- Add a dummy parameter updated with time to force browser/server to invalidate cache
         when we post updates to the web site. -->
    <s:current-date-time 
      attr="href" 
      format="table.css?datetime=[Y0001][M01][D01][H01][m01]" />
  </link>
  <script src="main.js" type="text/javascript" />
</head>

<body>

<p>
  This document was last updated: 
  <s:current-date-time format="[H01]:[m01] [z] on [FNn], [D] [MNn] [Y]" />.
</p>

<s:section>
  <s:heading>Introduction</s:heading>

  <p>...</p>

  <p>
    We will end our introduction with a teaser.  Everybody learning Chinese characters knows the
    phonetic hints in phono-semantic characters <p:mc>形聲字</p:mc> are ‘broken’ — the bane of 
    learners and native speakers alike. 
    Take a look
    at the following chart containing only a handful of the numerous examples of such characters.
  </p>

  <table class="sound-comparison">
    <caption>Some characters with the same phonetic component but diverging pronunciations</caption>

    <col class="row-number" />

    <colgroup>
      <col class="character" />
      <col class="gloss" />
      <col class="chinese" />
      <col class="japanese" />
    </colgroup>
    <colgroup>
      <col class="character" />
      <col class="gloss" />
      <col class="chinese" />
      <col class="japanese" />
    </colgroup>
    <colgroup>
      <col class="character highlight" />
      <col class="gloss highlight" />
      <col class="chinese highlight" />
      <col class="japanese highlight" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>

      <tr>
        <th></th>
        <th class="character">A</th>
        <th class="gloss">Gloss</th>
        <th class="chinese"><p:mc>中:普粵</p:mc></th>
        <th class="japanese"><p:j>日:呉漢</p:j></th>
        <th class="character">B</th>
        <th class="gloss">Gloss</th>
        <th class="chinese"><p:mc>中:普粵</p:mc></th>
        <th class="japanese"><p:j>日:呉漢</p:j></th>
        <th class="character">C</th>
        <th class="gloss">Gloss</th>
        <th class="chinese"><p:mc>中:普粵</p:mc></th>
        <th class="japanese"><p:j>日:呉漢</p:j></th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <s:merge-table-rows>
        <s:fragment><tr><th rowspan="2"><s:ordinal value="1" /></th></tr></s:fragment>
        <p:pcgk-comparison-table-block 
          char="痕" gloss="scar; trace"
          p="hén" c="han4" g="gon" k="kon" />
        <p:pcgk-comparison-table-block
          char="恨" gloss="resent, hate"
          p="hèn" c="han6" g="gon" k="kon" />
        <p:pcgk-comparison-table-block
          char="根" gloss="root"
          p="gēn" c="gan1" g="kon" />
      </s:merge-table-rows>

      <s:merge-table-rows>
        <s:fragment><tr><th rowspan="2"><s:ordinal value="2" /></th></tr></s:fragment>
        <p:pcgk-comparison-table-block 
          char="陽" gloss="sun; positive"
          p="yáng" c="joeng4" g="yau" />
        <p:pcgk-comparison-table-block 
          char="傷" gloss="wound, injury"
          p="shāng" c="shoeng1" g="syau" />
        <p:pcgk-comparison-table-block 
          char="湯" gloss="soup; hot water"
          p="tāng" c="tong1" g="tau" />
      </s:merge-table-rows>

      <s:merge-table-rows>
        <s:fragment><tr><th rowspan="2"><s:ordinal value="3" /></th></tr></s:fragment>
        <p:pcgk-comparison-table-block 
          char="者" gloss="person"
          p="zhě" c="ze2" g="sya" />
        <p:pcgk-comparison-table-block 
          char="豬" char-j="猪" gloss="pig; boar"
          p="zhū" c="zyu1" g="tyo" />
        <p:pcgk-comparison-table-block 
          char="都" gloss="city; capital"
          p="dū" c="dou1" g="tu" k="to" />
      </s:merge-table-rows>

      <s:merge-table-rows>
        <s:fragment><tr><th rowspan="2"><s:ordinal value="4" /></th></tr></s:fragment>
        <p:pcgk-comparison-table-block 
          char="樂" gloss="enjoy; happy"
          p="lé" c="lok9" g="raku" />
        <p:pcgk-comparison-table-block 
          char="礫" gloss="pebble; rubble"
          p="lì" c="lik7" g="ryaku" k="reki" />
        <p:pcgk-comparison-table-block 
          char="藥" gloss="medicine; drug"
          p="yào" c="joek9" g="yaku" />
      </s:merge-table-rows>

      <s:merge-table-rows>
        <s:fragment><tr><th rowspan="2"><s:ordinal value="5" /></th></tr></s:fragment>
        <p:pcgk-comparison-table-block 
          char="譯" char-j="訳" gloss="translate; explain"
          p="yì" c="yik9" g="yaku" k="eki" />
        <p:pcgk-comparison-table-block 
          char="驛" char-j="駅" gloss="station, stop"
          p="yì" c="yik9" g="yaku" k="eki" />
        <p:pcgk-comparison-table-block 
          char="擇" char-j="択" gloss="select, choose"
          p="zé" c="zaak9" g="dyaku" k="taku" />
      </s:merge-table-rows>
    </tbody>
  </table>

  <p>
    The above table is read as follows:

    <ul>
      <li>
        Each major row in the table (labeled <s:ordinal value="1" /> to <s:ordinal value="5" />) 
        contains three characters sharing the same
        phonetic component.  
      </li>
      <li>
        Across each row, the characters from the first two groups of columns 
        (labeled A and B), we see the modern Chinese pronunciations are similar.  The upper sub-row
        shows the Mandarin (<p:mc><strong>普</strong>通話</p:mc>); the lower sub-row shows the Cantonese 
        (<p:mc><strong>粵</strong>語</p:mc>).
      </li>
      <li>
        To the right of each Chinese pronunciation is the Japanese pronunciation.  
        As you may already know, characters get different readings in Japanese depending, among
        other things, the time period when they were imported.
        The upper sub-row gives the Go-on (<p:j><strong>呉</strong>音</p:j>) variant of the character's readings; the lower sub-row gives 
        the Kan-on (<p:j><strong>漢</strong>音</p:j>) reading.
        Wherever Go-on and Kan-on happen to be the same, they are combined into one cell.
      </li>
      <li>
        The Japanese readings may look a bit unfamiliar: they are in 
        <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Historical_kana_orthography" title="Wikipedia: Historical kana orthography">
        historical (etymological) spelling</a>, 
        which makes sound correspondences a lot more obvious.
      </li>
    </ul>
  </p>

  <p>
    Observe that the third group of columns (labeled C) has the seemingly exceptional pronunciation
    in Chinese.  For example, in row 1 the characters share the phonetic component <p:mc>艮</p:mc>, but
    <p:mc>根</p:mc> (cell C1) has the initial consonant <em>g</em> while 
    <p:mc>痕</p:mc> (cell A1) and <p:mc>恨</p:mc> (cell B1)
    has the initial consonant <em>h</em>.
  </p>
  <p>
    Now, most people intuitively understand that pronunciations of characters 
    are likely to have changed since they were first devised hundreds of years ago.  But the recurring patterns
    of similar pronunciations for similar-looking characters seen today would seem to suggest the 
    changes cannot be entirely random for each character.
    So then, for the ‘exceptional’ characters, were the ancients just drunkenly sloppy in spelling out their
    sounds?  When I was but a schoolkid, I certainly thought so.
  </p>
  <p>
    If we examine the table more closely, we see that the Japanese pronunciations in column group C 
    also seem to distinguish themselves from those in column groups A and B.  This suggests, firstly, that the
    characters already had diverging pronuncations very early on for them to manifest in both Chinese and Japanese.  
    Furthermore, we can spot the following:
    <ul>
      <li>
        In row <s:ordinal value="1" />, that the Japanese Go-on has a voiced consonant <em>g</em> in columns A and B
        but not in column C, so whatever difference the pronuncation turns out to be in ancient times
        might just have something to do with voicing and de-voicing. 
      </li>
      <li>
        In row <s:ordinal value="2" />, the pronunciation of all three characters seems ‘regular’ enough in Mandarin, 
        all having vowel <em>a</em>; and so does the Japanese.  Cantonese is the odd one out
        in that we have the contrasting vowels <em>oe</em> and <em>o</em>.  Yet, if we look at the
        Japanese, what is distinct about character C is that it is spelled with no <em>y</em>
        but characters A and B are.  Perhaps the ancient pronunciation only differs in the <em>y</em> sound
        which might explain the phonetic component <p:mc>昜</p:mc> being the same.
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
          The same thing happens in row <s:ordinal value="3" />, where column A and column B sound different enough
          already — with Japanese taking two different consonants <em>s</em> and <em>t</em> even. 
          Most native-language speakers (in any of the three languages) 
          probably do not realize the graphical component <p:mc>者</p:mc> occurring in 
          <p:mc>都</p:mc> even indicates any phonological value like in the characters 
          <p:mc>者</p:mc>, <p:mc>豬</p:mc> (and quite a few others like <p:mc>緒</p:mc>, <p:mc>署</p:mc>).  
          I certainly did not until I read <s:cite key="Dǒng 2008" pages="41–42" />!
        </p>
        <p>
          This particular series of characters is also discussed in
          <s:cite key="Xiàng 2023 Ⅰ" pages="81 &amp; 102" />.
        </p>
      </li>
      <li>
        In row <s:ordinal value="4" />, Japanese has consonant <em>r</em> corresponding to <em>l</em> in Chinese, naturally. 
        Both the Japanese <em>r</em> and the Chinese <em>l</em> disappear at the same time for
        the exceptional character.  But the vowel in Japanese does not really differ between
        the three characters, suggesting that <p:mc>藥</p:mc> has phonetic component <p:mc>樂</p:mc> because
        the two characters sounded closer than in modern Chinese dialects.
      </li>
      <li>
        In row <s:ordinal value="5" />, Japanese gains a consonant <em>d</em> or <em>t</em> to distinguish the character 
        from column C.  Under Go-on the vowel is <em>a</em> on all three characters, but changes
        under Kan-on except for character C, suggesting characters A and B were diverging further from C
        (particularly, with respect to the vowel) in the 
        time period between when Go-on and Kan-on got established
        (and thus long after the three characters got devised).
      </li>
    </ul>
  </p>

  <p>
    So, with scant knowledge of what ancient Chinese sounded like, by just comparing the reflexes from 
    just three modern languages, we have been able to partially uncover the mysteries
    surrounding these characters and their phonetic components.  
    This, I hope, convinces you that our investigation will prove interesting
    and fruitful.  
    Once we explore 
    ancient Chinese phonology more, we will soon find that all the observations 
    we have made are <em>no mere coincidences</em> but have logical explanations.
  </p> 

</s:section>

&conventions;


<s:section>
  <s:heading>What is Middle Chinese?</s:heading>

  <p>
    <s:term>Middle Chinese</s:term> <p:mc>中古漢語</p:mc> represents the stages of Chinese 
    presumed to have been spoken roughly between 200 AD to 1300 AD, from the start of the 
    Three Kingdoms period (after the Han dynasties)
    to the Song dynasties (before the invasion of China by the Mongols).  Informally, we may 
    treat it a language like any other in history, which can be subjected to linguistic
    study, e.g. using the comparative method.  But technically speaking, Middle Chinese is 
    a constructed system of pronunciation, which has been passed down to us through
    written records of philologists from that era and since.  
  </p>

  <p>
    We know, from the written record, that fairly divergent dialects of Chinese even 
    existed back then, so certainly no one could be said to have <em>spoken a single
    language</em> called "Middle Chinese".  However, what linguists have been able to deduce is that
    varieties of Chinese had evolved from a proto-language with the following characteristics:

    <ul>
      <li>
        Its spoken form was primarily monosyllabic: not only everyday words, but even vocabulary that
        we would consider rather specialized today, like names of species of plants and animals,
        consisted of one syllable. <s:cite key="Xiàng 2023 Ⅳ" sec="2" />
      </li>
      <li>
        Only later were multi-syllabic words  incorporated into everyday language, often replacing 
        old monosyllabic words as the latter became too ambiguous.   
        Not only because the limits on the number of distinguishable phonological 
        features were hit, preventing the coining of new words with new syllables, 
        but also individual monosyllabic words were increasingly overloaded with many shades of meaning, 
        or even completely new meanings, as society evolved to articulate new concepts.
        <s:cite key="Xiàng 2023 Ⅳ" sec="3" />
      </li>
      <li>
        It had a distinctive written form consisting of "characters", whose modern, evolved form
        are recognizable to many people today. 
      </li>
      <li>
        Each character was pronounced as one syllable.   
        For monosyllabic words that means one character
        corresponds to one word.  For compound words made of a series of monosyllabic morphemes, the
        compound word would be written with the corresponding characters to those monosyllabic morphemes.
        Genuinely multi-syllabic morphemes (usually disyllabic) would still be written with multiple
        characters even if though the characters may have no meaning outside of being part of the
        multi-syllabic morpheme. 
      </li>
      <li>
        The above key aspects of the language are retained to this day in modern Chinese dialects. 
      </li>
      <li>
        Many of the phonological changes in varieties of Chinese could be analyzed syllable-by-syllable
        — though not all, of course.  
        So we can effectively speak of a Chinese character having certain a "pronunciation" at a certain
        time and place, and how it changes throughout
        history across different dialects. 
      </li>
    </ul>
  </p>

  <p>
    The proto-language that Middle Chinese evolved from is called <s:term>Old Chinese</s:term>
    <p:mc>上古漢語</p:mc>.  Old Chinese is way beyond the scope of this article, and its re-construction
    is subject to considerable uncertainty.  But knowing some
    aspects of its evolution is still useful, in shedding light on certain pecularities of Middle Chinese.
    We will point out some of the salient details as we go along.
  </p>

</s:section>

<s:section>
  <s:heading>Primary sources on Middle Chinese</s:heading>

  <p>
    We give a brief overview of the major kinds of data we have on Middle Chinese.
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li>
      <s:term>Rhyme dictionaries</s:term>, which list out groups of characters that sound the same
      or similar. As the term implies, one of the purposes of rhyme dictionaries were to 
      help ancient poets write rhyming poetry.
    </li>
    <li>
      <s:term>Rhyme tables</s:term>, which organize all the syllables of the language systematically
      in two-dimensional tables, analogously to how we do the same today for Mandarin Chinese (e.g. 
      <s:cite key="Pīnyīn 2008" />).
    </li>
    <li>
      The ancient poetry whose verses are supposed to rhyme, thus giving clues to pronunciation.
    </li>
    <li>
      Other dictionary-like and expository texts written in ancient times. 
    </li>
  </ul>

  <p>
    For the moment, let us contrast the situation of Middle Chinese versus a Western language 
    written with an alphabet, say Ancient Greek.  Even though the sounds assigned to various letters 
    may change over time, and the spelling of words may become fossilized (i.e. retaining 
    etymological spellings that do not reflect current pronunciation anymore), intuitively nobody
    seriously doubts a fairly direct connection between how words are written versus how they sound.
  </p>

  <p>
    But because Chinese, until modern times, had never employed phonetic writing in a systematic manner,
    one may reasonably wonder how much value do Chinese historical records give.  To that point, 
    the evidence from the four categories of works mentioned so far can be fairly indirect.  
    The saving grace is that ancient Chinese philologists learned to analyze their language
    as ancient India did to 
    <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanskrit" title="Wikipedia: Sanskrit">Sanskrit</a>.
    (Though, as one might expect,
    ancient terminology and notation were nowhere as precise and unambiguous 
    as in modern linguistics.) 
  </p>

  <p>
    Finally, we have data that can be subject to the <em>comparative method</em>
    like linguistics applied to any other language:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li>
      Pronunciations or readings of characters in sino-xenic languages and Modern Chinese varieties.
    </li>
    <li>
      Phonetic transcriptions of known foreign terms/loanwords into Chinese characters.  
    </li>
  </ul>

  <p>
    To give an example that everybody can recognize, 
    the word <em>buddha</em> was, and continues to be to this day, phonetically approximated 
    by the character
    <p:mc>佛</p:mc>.  From this fact we may surmise that this character was originally
    pronounced with a <p:i>b-</p:i> initial consonant, despite it being pronounced today 
    as <p:py>fó</p:py> in Mandarin and <p:yp>fat⁶</p:yp> in Cantonese, though it is indeed
    pronounced as <p:jr>butu</p:jr> (<p:j>仏</p:j>) in Japanese.
  </p>

  <s:section>
    <s:heading>Rhyme dictionaries</s:heading>

    <p>
              , exemplified by the work <p:ac>廣韻</p:ac>,
          completed in 1011 AD in the Northern Song dynasty <s:cite key="Dǒng 2008" pages="58–59" />.
          Such dictionaries list out <s:term>rhymes</s:term>, which are sets of characters which end
          in a similar (but not necessarily the same) sound.  Each rhyme is represented by a head character <p:ac>韻目</p:ac>.

    </p>
        <p>
          In the first page, reproduced below, from the table of contents of the first volume of
          <p:ac>廣韻</p:ac>, 
          we can see 18 rhymes listed: <p:ac>東</p:ac>, <p:ac>冬</p:ac>, <p:ac>鍾</p:ac>, and so on.
          <img class="page" src="https://ytenx.org/static/img/DrakDzuonDang/volume1/p014.jpg" />
        </p>
        <p>
          Each rhyme is further divided into sub-groups of completely homophonous characters.  For instance,
          the first rhyme <p:ac>東</p:ac> contains the sub-groups <p:ac>東</p:ac>, <p:ac>菄</p:ac>, 
          <p:ac>鶇</p:ac> and so on, as shown below:
          <img class="page" src="https://ytenx.org/static/img/DrakDzuonDang/volume1/p015.jpg" />.
        </p>

  <blockquote>
    <p>
      It is mentioned that at the beginning of the Kāihuáng 開皇 era (AD 581–600) of the
      reign of Emperor Wen of Sui, there was a small gathering hosted by 
      <p:ac>陸法言</p:ac> (Lù Fǎyán), 
      where discussions about correct pronunciations came up. They noted that the 
      dialects at that time had considerable phonological differences, and a standard or
      correct pronunciation system was need by scholars and their students. Therefore,
      they compared the pronunciations from the south and the north and decided on
      the correct pronunciations, often with reference to older rhyme dictionaries, thus
      producing the first manuscript of the <p:ac>切韻</p:ac> (Qièyùn).
    </p>
  </blockquote>


  </s:section>

  <s:section>
    <s:heading>Rhyme tables</s:heading>

    <p>
    exemplified by <p:ac>韻鏡</p:ac>, compiled in c.a. 1131 AD – 1162 AD,
          during the Southern Song dynasty <s:cite key="Dǒng 1996" pages="112" />.  
        </p>

  </s:section>



</s:section>

&syllable;
&reflexes;

<s:section>
  <s:heading>Glossary</s:heading>

  <table>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th>English</th>
        <th>Chinese</th>
        <th>Japanese</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <th>Place of articulation</th>
        <td><p:mc>發音部位</p:mc></td>
        <td><p:j>調音点</p:j></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Manner of articulation</th>
        <td><p:mc>發音方法</p:mc></td>
        <td><p:j>調音法</p:j></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Bilabial (sound)</th>
        <td><p:mc>雙唇音</p:mc></td>
        <td><p:j><s:ruby>両【りょう】唇【しん】音</s:ruby></p:j></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Plosive (stop)</th>
        <td><p:mc>塞音</p:mc>, <p:mc>破音</p:mc></td>
        <td><p:j>破裂音</p:j></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Nasal (consonant)</th>
        <td><p:mc>鼻音</p:mc></td>
        <td><p:j><s:ruby>鼻【び】音【おん】</s:ruby></p:j></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Affricate</th>
        <td><p:mc>塞擦音</p:mc></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Fricative</th>
        <td><p:mc>擦音</p:mc></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Consonant</th>
        <td><p:mc>輔音</p:mc></td>
        <td><p:j><s:ruby>子【し】音【おん】</s:ruby></p:j></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Vowel</th>
        <td><p:mc>元音</p:mc></td>
        <td><p:j><s:ruby>母【ぼ】音【おん】</s:ruby></p:j></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Allophone</th>
        <td></td>
        <td><p:j>異音</p:j></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Complementary distribution</th>
        <td><p:mc>互補分佈</p:mc></td>
        <td><p:j>補い合う<s:ruby>分【ぶん】布【ぷ】</s:ruby></p:j></td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>

</s:section>

&bibliography;

</body>
</html>